thanks everybody for um coming to to
today's market seminar this is the last
seminar of um 2021. uh we've had a really good
year so thank you everybody uh for coming along uh
thank you to our speakers and thank you to our our
audience we've had a really good uh a good year
for anybody who hasn't um come to one of our
seminars before um general format is a loose
format is presentations of about 30 minutes
or so uh give or take and we kindly ask you
keep your microphones muted during that time
so it's not to interrupt uh the speaker and if
you do struggle with any internet connection um
if you turn off your camera and that can often
improve things at the end of the talk we'll have
uh time for a 10 to 15 minute uh question and
discussion session if you want to ask a question
we'll invite you to to unmute your microphone
um but if you don't want to um get your microphone
and by all means type a question into the chat and
one of our hosts will will read it out
for you and as always many of you are
are working at home or on unusual time
zones um so life is going on around us
uh greg you've been muted yeah there we go
so if you have to get up and go um please
uh please do so um and at the end there is
time for everybody to catch up with a bit
of a social um which isn't recorded and it's a
chance just to to catch up with everybody here
so today whoops so today i'm really
pleased to say that we've got uh marx here
um who is going to talk about um
neanderthals in the thought forest
so without much further ado i'll hand over to you
mark and thanks very much for for giving this talk
let me mute myself first and
then start sharing my screen
can you see my my screen
yeah yeah okay why is that
why is it not because yes and the pointer
and can you see the laser pointer too
uh so we're on the um um present review okay okay
well hello uh good afternoon everybody um today
sorry mark i think are you sharing on two screens
we can see the presenter view not the display view
sorry okay how do i change that uh if you
go to it should be display settings and then
yep swap presenter okay like that okay no ah
i have two screens but there were okay now i
can see you present the view on my other other
screen okay it was that was i didn't know that
okay good afternoon everybody today i will talk
about uh research that i did for my phd already
some some time ago um in recent years i've been
mainly working on uh the home and insights payload
lakes uh drilling projects uh but for two reasons
i will not be talking about that that today
one reason is that greg was already present at a
talk of mine some years ago which i talked about
the aspdp and even though those cores have a
very different age range and different research
question the the methodology from a preliminary
point of view is is quite similar and also um
this work uh of my phd i never really
presented for a more paleomagnetic
community so this is a good opportunity to do so
um it's a phd in paralytic archaeology so
it's going to be a bit archaeology heavy
so the title of my talk is uh nyantos in
the forest which was also the title of my
phd thesis and a correlation with the
blake event with their immune pulling zones
so i'm going to start with
some background information
as we know that modern humans are distributed all
over the globe but from the faults of record we
can infer that our ancestors had more limited
distribution and from one or more core regions
in africa our ancestors solely expanded
and contracted their geographical range
and with changes being attributed in the range
being attributed to climate change environmental
variation and technology technological innovations
or technological innovations for example
stone tool type development development
fire use that kind of thing that means
that understanding the ranges of hominins helps
us understand their climate and environmental
tolerance and their technology technological
and social skill set due to the long history
research history in france neanderthals are the
best known hominin species beside homo sapiens
but still the geographic range and especially the
modification in this race range through time are
poorly understood the migrations of nayanato the
theaters towards the middle and higher latitude
would be instrumental for understanding the
limitation in terms of biological and cultural
capacity capacities one of the key periods in
this aspect is the imminent switching in the uk
also known as the last interglacial mis5e the
the last and best documented interglacial stage
that the neanderthals were present in europe and
the other talk will argue that mis5e and indian
terminology should not be changed interchangeably
and that caution is needed when using these terms
and this figure you see actually like a palm set
of neonatal distributions so this is not a time
slice but actually quite a long duration of the
thought expand range of neanderthals over eurasia
during the 19th century and beginning of the 20th
century warm and temperate interglacial periods
like the present day were thought
to be ideal for survival hominins
because of the final diversity and the
climate climatically favorable conditions
although a lot of us are sitting in the
cold uh today and just i just heard um
but however during the 1980s british archaeologist
clive campbell argued that interglacial europe
may have formed a hostile environment
for hominins and that neanderthals lacked
social structures and especially like knowledge
and skills that would enable them to survive
in a way in other words the editors were
not clever enough to to survive in such uh
complicated environments an example for this is
for example that it is is that in the glacials
you have more solitary animals roaming the
forest while in other times you have large herds
in open plains and you can imagine that hunting
for a large herd in open plain is much easier than
hunting a solitary animal in the forest which
requires a lot of knowledge of the environment
hunting skills and communications which neonatals
are thought not to have had at least in the 80s
the lack of well-dated immune
sites seemed to support
this and this was essential to gamble's
theory however during the 1990s which is my
uh uh phd director and colleagues analyzed
in detail chronological archaeological
and bilateral paleo ecological records available
for the region and this showed that not only
archaeological sites were present in northwestern
europe but not in the united kingdom but also
that they represent were present in fully
interglacial the city's forest conditions
but even today the debate
about ecological tolerances
in neonatals is still ongoing particularly in
the north particularly in northwestern europe
with the real limits of their distribution both
in space and in time being an important issue
my research aimed to contribute to this debate
by developing a more precise correlation between
chronology and environmental conditions of certain
northwestern european sites with neonatal presence
and for chronology reviews surprise surprise
for australian magnetism one of the more recent
uh magnetic excursions the blake event that was
first described in 1969 by smith and forrester
and has been correlated with the mis5e in
marine corps at the time we started the research
the duration of the plague event was quite
short and was used as the base of the mis5e
and eemian and the late middle uh glycine boundary
at the end of this presentation i will
show that this is no longer the case
before going into the data from the
sites that we have studied i need to
say something about emin and mis5 terminology
in 1874 professor harting was the first to use
the term emilian after a river aimed in
the netherlands as a stratigraphic unit
near amsterdam amazfit in the netherlands he
noticed a consistent occurrence of sand and clays
with mollusks and diatoms and among them were
species with the mediterranean and west arbarian
occurrence and do not occur in present-day
netherlands as they prefer a warmer climate
during the 1920s pollen
research were able to identify
the non-molecules bearing levels of the eemian
and correlate them over large parts over europe
nowadays the lower boundary of the eemian
is placed where the three taxi exceed 50 percent
so here it is where the three exists 50 percent
of the terrestrial pollen some and the upper
boundary is placed when the this goes below
the 50 percent and it's in between the vegetation
of the saline and the vaccine glaciers the
duration of the immune in northwestern europe
has been estimated at 11 000 years by far
counting an extrapolation of sedimentation rate
at the german side of bisping by miller in 1974.
the virus occurred in the lower part
of the sequence so the lower part of
the sequence as you can see here number one is
extremely detailed so 100 years 200 years 450
but the higher up you go into the
sequence there are no more virus present
and those durations of these different pollen
zones are estimated in segmentation rate so
they're the longer duration but also there's
more error margin in those in those estimates
in southern europe actually the ratio uh
okay well sorry i have to go back in one step
the iteration of the immune in northern europe
has been estimated 11 000 years while in southern
europe it has been estimated estimated as
16 000 euro that's 16 000 years which is a
quite a big difference of 5 000 years and which
is a problem if you want to use the immune as
a chronostratigraphic unit for the mis curve
this is less the iconicity is less of an issue
because the boundaries are arbitrary and
reflect the global ice uh volume chains
and also pale magnetic excursions
are thought are believed to be
global in over all over the world problem in
the in time sorry you know what i'm about to say
so next these are the sites that i want to talk
about is noimark in in eastern germany in france
and written in the netherlands very close to
the type locality of the eemian in amazfort in
amsterdam let's start with norm mark or no magnort
as it's officially called it's located south 10km
southwest of of hala west of leipzig and actually
the sides consist of three sites norway not one
two and three and it's situated in the gisental
an area which has been known for brown coal mining
over the last 300 years due to the large-scale
mining activities research has been going on
for the last three decades and norma north 1 was
discovered in 1985 by professor tomei and was
excavated until 1990 in 1995 and then that same
year the normal site two and three were discovered
according to professor mania
the age of norman norton one
can be placed in interstate interstadial and
there's an age of around 220 000 years ago
and a similar age uh was estimated for norman
r2 but it was a within the team there was a big
discussion about the age of norm ignore 2 leading
to a detailed research of that site here you can
see normal nord one with a flintstone stone
tool scatters along the edges of the basin
and a lot of final remains all through the
basin and some with butcher marks and this
is actually the normal r2 segment we'll talk about
and these are these squares are 100 by 100 meters
mining stopped in the 1980s 1990s and the man-made
valley has been made into a recreation lake
before the archaeological sites would be lost
for research a large scale rescue excavations
took place from 2004 to 2008 excavating
a round and yield a rich archaeological
assemblage of around 20 000 middle paleolithic
artifacts and 120 000 fauna remains
the final remains uh include a lot
of warm tempered species including uh
straight dusk elephants one of the
tusks you see being excavated here
in the lower part uh rhino bovets ecwid deer beer
bear and all smoke cannon force and a lot of other
animals in order to develop a fine-grained paleo
environmental and chronological framework for this
unique archaeological record the basic info was
studied at a by wide range of disciplines and
also because of the disagreement about the age of
the site and these studies yield climate climatic
and chronological proxy records which are great
relevance to the study of the last international
the infill the genesis and the artifact pairing
deposits in particular were meticulously studied
and documented in a large number of sections
throughout excavation a key section is
how to profile this even or main profile 7 hp 7
and it cut through the deepest part of the infill
and the section will sample the wide range
of techniques for paleo environmental studies
including sedimentological morphological studies
further pollen make microbuture micro botanical
remains mollusks et cetera et cetera finally for
a high high-resolution perimeter examples were
taken at five centimeter intervals uh over the
entire sequence all data indicates a geological
rapid infiniting of a shallow basin and micro
morphological study shows that the cementation
was nearly continuous process without pronounced
solar formations in period of non-deposition
for the genetic research we took 184 samples
of which 159 were taken with dedicated perspex
sample containers and 25 samples were drilled
in the pedigree laboratory of fort hovdak of the
university of utrecht we the samples were step
wisely magnetized using af up to 100 mini tesla
thermally up to 600 degrees and a selected
set of samples were first heated up to 205
degrees to remove the viscous component and then
followed by an alternating field demagnetization
here we see two side of the diagrams of
normal north 2 no drm is indicated in these
two diagrams but it was present in some in some
samples where no clear endpoint direction was
observed the samples were labeled of quality
2 and later excluded from the interpretation
i just want to point out that none of the
samples inside that diagram are fully reversed
which you can also see in this figure we plot a
result next to the stratographic column here it
shows a stereographical hint zone from
7.7 to 1.7 meters with clear deviation
of declination and inclination and we associate
this zone with the blake event when we combine
it with the pollen data from professor barclays we
can make an age estimate of the duration estimate
of the of the blake events because we as i told
before we know the duration of this zone one
two three etc also it's very important uh that
to see that actually the blake event here starts
before pulling zone one that's a key observation
so when we combine this date of the pollen with
the duration of the blade event although there
are some excursion directions here but there
are low quality sort of excluded we come to a
duration of 3400 years plus or minus 350 years
also a lot of rock mechanism was done i
just want to show the slide that it was done
i'm not going to go into the into the
detail of the rock mag if people are
interested i can supply the publication but
of all the sites detailed rock magnetism
was done and they showed different
magnetic carriers in all on all sides
also we know from course in the mediterranean
the location of the blake event in relationship
to sup propel s5 we know that the blake event
has been discovered here's a propeller s5
the black event is on top of it
superpowers 5 on top of it etc
and we know it also in the relationship
with the m marine i stop state curve five e
um from the core of the western iberia of the
being plateau we also also know that eemian was
estimated at sixteen thousand year starts well
it starts before the mi5e plateau over here
and from the same core we combine this
figure because the black event also was
discovered in net core but unfortunately in
one publication you use depth in the other
publication they used age but fortunately they
in the supplementary information they used a
correlation tables published so
we could correlate this figure
and we see that here that the
blake event of the same core
starts well starts around the top or after the
top of the mis5e curve but well after the imian 5e
which is opposite to what we've seen in in
normwork so when we combine all this data
uh we plot the start of the eemian in the
the western iberian core the md 95 2042
uh we plot the the duration and the h of the
sub lapel s5 and then as we know from normal
that the blake event just starts slowly a
little bit before the start of the eemian
at normal number two we built that here and then
we plot the start of the immunity normal r2 we
see it and then we see that there's actually
quite of a large lag time between the start
of the eemian in southern europe and the start of
the union in northern europe again a big an issue
for the alien as a cornerstratographic unit um the
next slide i want to briefly mention is kaur i'm
not going to go in big and in detail about this
side just it's a site in the in the psalm valley
uh formed by uh by too fast and travertine
and travel times formed by a little spring a
little bit uphill but no pollen were discovered
and the sequence is quite short but we did find
excursion directions and together with osl data
also we have interpreted this as the blake event
and again you see well you see a declination
of 197 but another but a positive inclination
and but and sometimes you do have a negative
inclination but not again not a fully reversed
declination quite similar directions
as a norm marked but not fully reversed
the last side i want i want to mention is is
written which is not an archaeological site
but it's a site that we drilled with my
colleague john paters well actually he
paid for it with his phd research he was
funded by an old company so and this is
a a core of 25 meters and it was non-rotational so
this was pushed downwards without any rotational
movement so ideal for paleomagnetism because
you do not lose the asymmetry orientation
as you know in course often excursions or
reversals are identified based on the incarnation
but during the blake event this incarnation
is not always of of of uh not always fully
reversed so not of much help with the
location of the site was chosen because we
it was the high probability to find
a complete indian pollen sequence
okay so here is the sampling took place then
perspex uh sample containers were taken but also
uh quartz uh handmade quartz containers were
made for thermal demagnetization and in total
we took 252 pentaminatic samples over 25 meters
180 of them for a thermal demagnetation on a 34
for afd magnetization and this up we magnetized
up to 100 mini tesla and we use the so-called
per-component protocol because we believe that
iron sulphides could be dominant here i showed two
thermal magnetization diagrams of of that core
and you can already tell by the the latest steps
that in the indeed iron sulfites are are quite
dominant in this interpretation because after
350 degrees the samples are are like uh are like
empty and again no not fully reversed when we plot
our paleomagnetic data next
to the stereographic column
we again see that the black event starts
before the top of the eemian pollen zone
here e1 unfortunately we didn't drill
deep enough to find the lower boundary
uh but in different to to normal to it it lasts
up to after pawn zone six or after the top of
the inion so here the blade event has a duration
that covers the complete eemian which would mean
that the breaking the restoration of 11 000
years but then again the complete duration
of the eemian is is an estimate especially large
apart there's a lot of margin of error of the last
of these zones that are estimated to be
four thousand years at the same time um my
quality of my mark born in the universe of oxford
estimated also the duration of the big event using
uh marine corps and um thorium uranum access
authorium excess 230xs for sedimentation rate
in the estimated duration of the blade around
6500 years so a lot longer than previous thought
but there's a bit of a difference
with my estimate but um again the
full duration of the in northwestern europe
is is quite rough it's quite a rough estimate
combining uh this data in the in this new figure
again shows uh that the black event starts after
supper by s5 that the duration is probably
longer than we estimated in three thousand four
in the years in normal and that there's a large
delay of around 10 000 years between the mis-5
5e start and the start of the eemian in
northwestern europe so why is it why does
this matter for uh for archaeology like like i
showed before we have an uh archaeology we have
uh neonatals present in kaur during the imian
uh but if you uh place the start of the eemian
uh with a long delay instead of a like a similar
delay between north and western europe it has
has consequences for the uh for what happens if
you arrive to eastern europe and the sea level uh
in sea level stand so if you arrive at the eemian
at the same time as the image starts here then the
sea level is still low but if the immune starts
uh significantly late by the time you arrive
with your in the immune here actually the the the
the channel is completely filled making a crossing
uh quite complicated and that aspect is uh
why it's important for the undertale range and
one more slide that i showed before so these
are the difference between the 2010 and 2020
chronographic chart so no longer is the the blake
the base of the eemian and no longer uh sorry um
the blatant is no longer the base
of the eemian and no longer the
base of the the middle twice
the same as you can see that the
the duration is longer uh it has been moved up a
bit to come back to the lake middle school middle
late middle plexing boundary and um and it's
not no longer used as the base of the eemian
and that was it's i don't know
how long i lasted actually
that was perfect thank you very much mark
uh we can all give mark our virtual round
of applause for um a really interesting talk
here so i think uh we can open up the floor um
to questions if anyone has been you can raise
your virtual hand and i'll invite you to to unmute
nobody's got a question i've got i've got
one to sort of kick off and i mean maybe you
mentioned it i i wasn't quite sure i mean
you were talking about how the email is is
is uh starts at different periods based upon
location in europe so what what actual markers
are used to donate um the onset of the immune is
it sort of by stratigraphic it's a pollen zone
okay so so when the three taxa reach uh over 50
percent of the terrestrial pollen some that's
where the base of the immune is okay and that's
well it's yeah but using uh flora and fauna as
a chronostratographic marker is a problem but
but the immune is a cornerstone of marker but
not a good one in my in well yeah
yes so now i understand why there
is a geographic and climactic depends
on on where this boundary appears then
yeah yeah but that was one of the comments in the
review is it's like yeah but you're saying that
there is a delay onset but it cannot be because
it's the kind of stereographic marker yes but
um kathy you have your hand up yeah
yeah i do um i'm i think i missed it
um but uh what i understood you to say is that
the length of the blade is variable with location
no i wasn't sure how many how broad your location
coverage was because i guess it wasn't i don't
depends on the location it's just that in
normal north the the top of the sequence
the quality of the data was lower
and i decided to exclude quality 2
from the interpretation so there are quality two
excursion directions but i had already decided to
exclude them um so now with hindsight if you go
back actually here there is a there is there are
indications of blake also the upper sequence of
of of normal two and why the quality is is uh is
not good it's probably because that has been more
nearer to the servers and have been more oxidized
so uh but there's of course it's different
like mark bourne did it did a detailed study
of a core and he used uh the sedimentation
that he estimated six and a half thousand
so if i estimate that the in in written
the whole duration of the eemian
it's based on what we think is the duration
of the imminent and there's an and there's a
quite large margin of error in the especially
the top part which is the the longest part
so i think six and a half thousand could be well
or but there's of course margin in mark barnes
work there's also a margin of error so i think if
you come to more than seven thousand years i think
it's uh i think it's quite likely uh and there's
uh you don't have any uh paleo intensity records
that would uh help in determining that uh i do
but let me see i haven't looked at them in a while
but but you don't you're dealing here
with a terrestrial record so it's not
you have you're quite limited i have a record but
it was not yeah i have it here in front of me it's
not quite useful because it's not just not long
enough you need a longer sequence to do something
to say something thank you thanks very much kathy
and does anybody else have any other questions
uh uh uh yeah thanks thanks mark for this
the nice talk um i i just wanted have
are you following this um the paper by jim
channel and and vignotti about this extinction
of the neanderthals and the relationship to the
to the last trump excursion and and you have an
opinion on the what happened at the black event
if that's actually true or not well i i have not
read the response yet there has been a response
in science i think last week all right but um
which i haven't read yet but uh first of all i
think it's called the adam's event he's called it
well my first reaction is why not during the blake
event this which is a lot longer and and but this
this type of arguments that uh extinctions
and cultural innovations of hominins are
related to uh to to reversals or pain intensity
lows has been a along already since the 60s
and there's so many uh lows in magnetic
intensity so many reversals and so many
things happening that you can always
make a correlation of everything
so i'm i'm i'm not convinced
uh at all uh now big no
all right thanks oh thanks very much
uh anita you have have your hand up
yes if i can if nobody has those questions for now
yeah go for it okay i have several questions but
one is i don't know if you've seen our latest
paper on the flint absolutely intensity so i
guess if you could uh i'm happy to discuss this
further but he could recover some material of
like flint material from those uh sites uh
i think it would be an invaluable source for
for checking uh the valentine's day absolutely i
don't i don't know you wrote you wrote that paper
yes i will i will email every
minute to you send it to me
in doing it yeah that's great that's
great the the flint tends to be weak
but there is a matter of magnetic enhancement in
some of them that will allow to obtain absolute
intensity i will further you and some of
my some of the flint is burnt also yeah
yes normal ignored so some of the some of the
the the thermal luminescence was done in flint
and uh there's also there also cooking stones
and uh we tried to use rock magnetism on the
cooking stones but it was not the the
problem is that they're the the granites
and it was not conclusive yeah we got it published
because a lot of things other things happened but
the the this in this setting rock magnetism
didn't work for identifying um cooking stones
yeah i'm happy to discuss it further but i
guess there were just a few studies before
before the one i'm gonna forward to you um so it's
kind of kind of a new thing um this so it would
be really important to get uh pollen absolutely
intense for the black event around like even but i
guess especially if you have some burn flints yeah
that would be even better yeah yeah which they are
and um and then i have a question that regards
me um so the black event it's typically uh
constructed by two sub events and it's shown
also in your data if you go back to your
uh inclination that means sugars uh sorry
2011 paper we did do like a like the uh what
do you call that like the polar one ring
but i'm not that convinced anymore about it
so i haven't used it also because this is
just only part of uh because i think now that
the black event is longer so i here i haven't
in written i haven't done it okay is that what you
mean like the the the the migration of uh vgp vgp
no i actually meant the uh the feature itself
it shows like a double double sub events you can
see from the paper by oseta 2012 from some time
in spain yeah in spain yeah yeah yeah and they
actually so the duration finally if you consider
they all it would be maybe it would be maybe like
for four or five thousand years which is within
the exclusion the duration of discussion we that
we've seen somewhere else say de la shum yeah
but is is is thought to be a lot shorter than the
black yeah yeah there is there is actually a great
a debate about the duration of the lashank as well
and the fact that may not be a global event or it
is a global event but uh not so it could be the
acronyms yeah i guess yeah okay maybe cathy
can help me or sanya i think i'm working on
the event now as well a little bit more yeah
yeah i think the black event is easier to find
kathy you admitted yourself you wanted to
say something oh yeah i was just going to
say that i think uh maybe sanya should chime in
here but uh what we see in uh our attempts to
figure out what's going on with the champ is that
it's followed by this period of generally low
intensity where there seem to be a lot of regional
events rather than any kind of global event
and that really complicates the issue
for using excursions as global markers
yeah yes thanks thanks cotton yes i mean the
black has been found with this double feature
in several places and of around the
kind of the globe so that could kind of
chip in toward like a more of a global event yeah
but i i don't i i don't see it in this data okay
all right thanks uh i don't want to
take up space from anyone else if
anyone answers the question please
go ahead otherwise have another one
greg yeah well i mean if nobody else has any
quick questions any time you can take up the
last question for today oh no no i don't want
to pick up the last question somebody else comes
thanks very much thank you very much you're very
welcome okay we'll we'll we'll bring it to we'll
bring it to a close there so i think we can
we can all thank mark again for uh another
fantastic talk and for rounding off um 2021 for us
cheers mark um let me just grab this screen share
so just before everybody um uh disappears off
um just a reminder that was at the last um
seminar of of 2021 um i want to thank
again every everybody who has attended
the seminars over the last year or so uh and
uh thanks to to all of our speakers we've had a
a great range of presentations uh across a wide
range of topics uh and it's been really it's been
really fun and really enjoyable um we will be back
um in in 2022 and we are um recruiting speakers uh
and as always we're uh wanting to encourage
uh early career scientists to to to give up
our markets presentation uh so if anybody uh would
like to give a presentation themselves or i would
know anybody who would like to give one please
by all means get in touch and put forward that
recommendation and if anybody has missed any of
the seminars and from from this year um and and
from last year as well and they are all now on our
uh magnets youtube channel um and mark's talk will
be put up there a little bit later this week and
just i don't have an official announcement but um
we will also be most likely including the uk
magnetic interactions um meeting which will run in
early january next year and so keep your eyes open
for that on our youtube channel early next year
but thanks everybody for coming along to magnets
and we'll see you all in the new year cheers